In this plot, we will introduce the "Central Limit Theorem,"
which is probably the single most important theorem in the theory of probability.
The theorem helps to explain
why the Gaussian or Normal distribution finds such widespread applications in natural and social sciences.
Briefly stated, it says that
the sum of N independent random variables,
which can be drawn from any arbitrary,
but well-behaved distributions will converge to a Gaussian distribution in the limit of large N.
We will discuss this in more detail later,
but first we will begin by working out some practical examples
that show the central limit theorem in practice.
In a previous lesson,
we introduced the binomial distribution P(n,M),
which describes a random process with two possible outcomes.
The standard example is that of a coin toss,
which can come up heads with probability p,
and tails with probability (1-p).
The probability to observe n heads after M throws is given by Eq. (C6).
In the limit when both n and M are very large,
we have seen that the binomial distribution converges to the Gaussian distribution
with average μ_1=Mp and variance σ^2=Mp(1−p).
We will see that
this is a trivial application of the central limit theorem.
It works because the result of each coin toss is given by
an independent random process with a well-defined average and variance.
While the proof for the equivalence has been given in the supplemental note,
let us examine this by performing numerical experiments for various values of M using Python.
As always,
we begin by importing the necessary numerical and graphical libraries.
In this code example,
we assume we are using a fair coin, such that p = 0.5.
The experiment consists in performing M coin tosses
and counting the number of heads.
To get reliable statistics,
we repeat this for N = 100,000 times,
and calculate the histogram of the data.
The sampling is performed in one line using numpy's built-in binomial function,
and the sampled data is stored as an array X of size N.
Remember each element of the X array contains the number of heads after M coin tosses.
We plot the histogram using the "hist" function.
Finally, we compare the results of our experiment with
the corresponding Gaussian distribution shown in Eq.(C1).
For this, we generate an array of x values
in a range 5 standard deviations to the right and left of the average value,
and calculate the theoretical Gaussian distribution over this array.
If you run this code example,
the results are plotted and overlaid on the histogram.
You should repeat this experiment for several values of M=1, 2, 4, 10, 50, 100 and 1000
to see how the histogram converges towards the Gaussian distribution.
The convergence is assumed in the limit of large n and M.
In practice, you will see that
a value of M = 50 already gives quite good agreement between the two distributions.
Let us discuss what we have seen in the experiments.
First we define a stochastic variable "s"
which gives the result of a single binary choice
that can be either 0 or 1.
The total number of heads, after M tosses, is given by the sum of all "s",
from the 1st to the M-th choice.
This defines a new stochastic variable n of M.
First, consider the case of a single coin toss for M=1,
for which n of M is the same as a single binary choice s,
as shown in Eq.(D1).
Since this random variable is drawn from a binomial distribution,
the average and variance are given by Eqs. (D2) and (D3).
Namely, the average number of heads
from one coin toss is equal to p, and the variance is equal to p*(1-p).
Now, consider the case for arbitrary M.
As we already discussed before,
n of M is given by the sum all "s" up to the M-th choice,
or equivalently, as the sum of M independent single coin toss results,
n of M=1 as shown in Eq.(D4).
In the limit when M is very large,
we have already proven that this converges to a Gaussian.
The average and variance of this distribution
is just the average and variance of the distribution for a single coin toss
multiplied by M as shown in Eqs. (D5) and (D6).
The previous relation between binomial and Gaussian distributions is
in fact an example of the Central Limit Theorem.
It is valid not only for the sum of random variables drawn from binomial distributions,
but it is applicable to any distributions with finite variance.
Thus, assume we have a set of M independent random variables,
which are drawn from the same distribution
given by n of M=1 with average and variance μ_1 and σ^2 of M=1.
The sum of these random variables is itself a random variable,
and in the limit when M is very large,
it converges to a Gaussian distribution.
The average and variance of n of M >> 1 are given by Eqs. (D8) and (D9),
which are indeed generalizations of Eqs. (D5) and (D6).
The average and variance of this sum are then
M times the average and variance of the individual distributions.
One of the most useful forms of the Central Limit Theorem appears when
considering the average of a series of stochastic variables, not just the sum.
As before,
let n of M=1 be a series of stochastic variables.
we assume that
they have average and variance of μ_1 and σ^2 of M=1.
They should be independent and identically distributed,
but other than that
they can be drawn from any distribution with a finite variance.
The average of these stochastic variables is given by
the weighted sum in Eq. (D10).
Apart from the factor of 1/M,
this is exactly the same as we considered in the previous example.
Now, we know that in the limit of very large M
the distribution of this variable converges to a Gaussian.
However, because of the 1/M factor in Eq. (D10)
the average and variance are now given by Eqs. (D11) and (D12).
Notice that
the average value of n of M is now equal to the average value of n of M=1.
More importantly,
the variance of n of M is the variance of n of M=1 divided by M.
Let us see another example of the Central Limit Theorem in practice.
Now, instead of a binomial distribution,
let us consider a continuous uniform distribution.
We define a stochastic variable "x" of M=1,
which is uniformly distributed between the unit interval.
Thus, the probability density of observing any valuable x is constant,
and equal to one
if x lies in the unit interval,
and zero if it is outside.
The average and variance can be easily calculated analytically,
and are given by 1/2 and 1/12, respectively.
Now, define a new stochastic variable x of M,
which is the sum of M of these uniform random variables.
In the limit when M is very large,
x of M is described by a Gaussian distribution with average and mean given by Eqs. (D8) and (D9).
In this case, the average is just M/2 and the variance is M/12.
In this numerical experiment, we will verify that
the sum of uniformly distributed random numbers converges to a Gaussian distribution
with average and variance defined in Eqs. (D17) and (D18).
In the code example,
we first set M, the number of random variables to add.
You should try with several values of M,
such as M=1, 2, 4, 10 and 100
to see how the distribution converges to a Gaussian.
Thus, one experimental run consists of generating M random variables,
and adding them to generate a sample for the cumulative variable.
We store these in the array X.
To obtain reliable statistics,
we repeat this experiment N = 100,000 times.
Then, we plot the histogram of X
together with the corresponding theoretical Gaussian distribution.
The two should be equal in the limit
when M is very large.
In practice, how many uniform random variables
must you add to obtain a Gaussian random variable?
As you should see for yourselves,
adding just 10 uniform random variables is already enough
to reproduce a distribution which is very close to a Gaussian distribution.