In this plot, I will demonstrate how to generate random numbers
from the Gaussian, binomial, and Poisson distributions using Python.
Also, we will examine the distribution of the generated random numbers
using the "histogram" function, and compare them with the exact results.
This is a list of frequently used commands defined in "numpy.random" library.
The first command "seed" is used to initialize the seed of the random number.
This specifies the initial state of the generator.
The second command "rand" generates uniform random numbers between 0 and 1
in a multi-dimensional array of the specified shape.
The third command "randn" works like "rand"
but draws the random numbers from a standard normal distribution.
The fourth and fifth commands, "binomial" and “poisson,"
generate random numbers from the binomial and Poisson distributions.
The sixth command "choice"
generates random samples from the specified set.
We will use this function to perform a random walk simulation later.
Gaussian and uniform random numbers can be generated also by "normal" and "uniform" functions,
but we will use the "randn" and "rand" functions instead.
First, we import the common libraries for today's lesson.
"math" library contains mathematical functions defined by the C standard,
such as the "factorial" function.
Let us first generate random numbers from a Gaussian distribution.
In the code example shown here,
we set the average and the standard deviation to be 0 and 1, respectively.
With this choice, the distribution is called the standard normal distribution.
Here we generate one hundred thousand random numbers using an initial seed 0.
The fifth line is the main operation of this example,
where an array of "N" random numbers is generated from a Gaussian distribution
with the given average and standard deviation,
and stored as an array X.
From the 6th line to the end,
we have the code used to plot the random numbers.
If you run the code example,
you will see the "N" red points distributed around zero,
mostly between -2 and +2.
Next, let us examine the distribution of random numbers
we have just generated in the previous code example,
and compare it with the Gaussian distribution function shown here.
In this code example,
the first line calculates and plots the histogram of the random numbers
stored in X using a single "hist" command.
The remaining part is only to plot the Gaussian distribution function Eq.(D1)
and to draw the figure.
As you can see in the figure,
the agreement between the two is almost perfect.
Next, we calculate the auto-correlation function defined in Eq.(D2)
for the sequence random numbers we have generated.
Note that we will study the correlation function in detail next week.
For now, what we need to know is that
the correlation function gives a measure of how "related" two variables are.
In this case,
we are interested in the correlation between the random numbers.
In other words,
if I know what number just came out of the generator,
what can I say about the other numbers
that have come out already or will come from now?
If the correlation is zero as given in Eq.(D4),
knowing one random number
tells me absolutely nothing about the other random numbers that can come out.
This is expected for any good random number generators.
In this lesson, we will use the correlation function
to confirm two basic properties of a random sequence.
The first confirmation is on its variance,
which should be equal to the square of the standard deviation, as shown in Eq.(D3).
The second confirmation is on the independency of the random numbers,
as given by Eq.(D4).
In the code example shown here,
we first define the "auto_correlate" function, which calculates Eq.(D3),
using the "numpy" library's own "correlate" function.
If you run this code example,
you can see that the variance of the random numbers does in fact agree with the theoretical value,
which is equal to the square of the standard deviation.
Also, we see that the correlation between distinct random numbers is zero,
as shown in the figure.
This assures us that
the different random numbers are independent of each other.
Stochastic variables satisfying this property are referred to as "white noise."
Now, let us perform the same experiment,
but this time drawing the random numbers from a binomial distribution.
As we have seen,
this describes the distribution of the results for a random choice from two possible outcomes.
The typical example is that of a coin toss.
On every toss,
we can obtain heads with probability p,
and tails with probability (1-p).
If the coin is fair,
then we of course expect both p and 1-p = 0.5.
This is the case we will consider.
Here, we are interested in looking at the number of head or success results
after 100 coin tosses.
To obtain reliable statistics,
we perform this experiment 100,000 times,
and each time we count the number of times head appears.
The code shown here generates the results of the experiment,
"number of heads after 100 coin tosses,"
for 100,000 trials, using the single command "binomial."
The results are then stored in X and plotted.
As you can see,
all the results are scattered around an average of 50,
and are almost all contained within the range between 30 and 70.
We again compare the distribution with the expected theoretical result.
The histogram is calculated and plotted by calling “hist" command
and then we compare the exact distribution with the "binomial" function.
As you can see in the figure,
the agreement between the two is again good.
Now let us check the correlation between the random numbers.
We use the same auto-correlate function as before.
To compare with the theory,
we compute the exact value for i=0,
which is given by Eq. (D9),
and should be equal to the square of sigma.
In this case that is 25.
Let us run the code example shown here to calculate the correlation function.
For i=0, we can confirm that
the variance of the random numbers agrees with the expected theoretical value 25.
In addition, we see that
there is no correlation between different random numbers.
Finally, let us perform the experiment using the Poisson distribution.
As discussed before,
this can be used to describe the probability of n "events"
occurring within some time interval,
assuming the expected value is a.
The typical example would be the number of requests
received by a website within a one-hour time period.
Here, we set the expected value, or average value "a" to be 10,
and we generate 100,000 random numbers.
As before, this can all be done in a single line,
using the "numpy" library functions.
The results are stored in X and plotted.
As you can see,
all the results are scattered around an average of 10,
and fall within the interval between 0 and 20.
Again, we compare the distribution with the expected theoretical result.
As you can see, the agreement is excellent!