In the previous plot, we already see that the diffusion constant of Brownian particles is determined through
the long-time limit of the mean square displacements.
In this plot, we derive the definition of the diffusion constant
in an alternative way using the linear response theory.
The result is an example of the so-called Green-Kubo formula,
which can define transport coefficients
in terms of equilibrium correlation functions of corresponding variables.
Let us consider a Brownian particle under the influence of an external drift force in the x-direction.
The Langevin equation we introduced in the previous plot is simply modified by
adding the external force on the right hand side as shown in Eq. (41).
Understanding how a system "responds" to such an external force or perturbation provides
valuable information on the dynamical properties of the system.
This is precisely what linear response theory allows us to do.
It measures the response of the system to an external perturbation,
under the assumption that the response is linear in this perturbation.
The first question we want to ask is
how does the system reach a steady state under this external force.
Thus, we take the steady state average of Eq. (41),
in the limit where the force is held constant for infinitely long time.
The limit of each term in Eq. (41) is given by the following equations.
By definition, the change in velocity should be zero in the steady state.
This means that the velocity is constant
and it should be exactly zero along the y and z directions.
Thanks to the properties of the random force,
its average should also be zero.
Finally, since the external force is constant,
its average is simply F_0 in the x direction.
Thus, we see that we only need to consider the dynamics along the x direction
since motion along y and z will average out to zero.
Taking the long time average of Eq. (41) on both sides,
we see that the steady-state drift velocity is given by F_0
divided by the friction constant zeta.
Then, using the Einstein relation,
we can rewrite the steady-state velocity in terms of the diffusion coefficient
and the thermal energy as shown in Eq. (42).
Finally, solving for D we obtain Eq. (43).
This tells us that the diffusion constant can also be obtained from
the steady-state velocity of a particle driven by an external force trough a fluid.
In contrast, in the previous plot we derived the diffusion coefficient
in terms of the mean-squared displacement of a particle diffusing in a fluid.
Let us now introduce the basics of linear response theory.
Its formal derivation is not treated in this course,
but can be found in several text books including
"Basic concepts for simple and complex liquids,"
and "Non-equilibrium statistical mechanics."
In the linear response theory,
we assume that the system is evolving in time with an equilibrium Hamiltonian H_0.
Then, an external force F(t) is applied to the system,
which gives rise to change in the Hamiltinan,
from H_0 to H_0+H'(t).
H'(t) is the energy gain describing the coupling of the external force to the system.
By definition, H' is written as -A*F(t),
and A is said to be the conjugate variable to F.
Now, consider how the average of a dynamical variable B changes under the external perturbation H'.
Let the average of B at equilibirum, under H_0, be denoted as B_0.
Under the perturbed Hamiltonian, H_0 + H',
the average of B at time t will deviate from B_0 by an amount of Delta B.
Here, we stress that
B_0 is calculated as an average over the original Hamiltonian H_0,
whereas the deviation Delta B is calculated over the perturbed Hamiltonian.
Using linear response theory,
we can compute the time evolution of Delta B, provided that the external force is "small" enough.
Then, to the first order in the perturbation,
the time evolution of Delta B, under the external force F,
is given by a convolution of Phi_BA and F.
Where Phi_BA is the response function,
and the integral is taken from -infinity to t.
This result is extremely useful,
because Eq. (44) predicts the temporal value of B under the influence of an external force solely
from the equilibrium properties of the system in the absence of any external forces!
Notice that, as given in Eq. (45),
the response function is defined as the cross correlation function of A dot and B
under equilibrium Hamiltonian.
We see that linear response theory allows us to connect averages at equilibrium, under H_0,
with averages out of equilibrium, under H_0 + H'.
As an example, let us revisit the problem of calculating the self-diffusion constant of a particle,
now using linear response theory.
Assume that we have a single particle at equilibrium in a fluid.
At time t=0, we turn on an external potential,
which applies a constant external force on the particle.
Without loss of generality, we can set the force to act along the x-direction
and define the coordinates such that R = 0 at t = 0.
Mathematically, this force is represented as a constant amplitude F_0
multiplied with the Heaviside step function Theta(t)
which equals to 1 for t larger than 0,
and 0 otherwise, as illustrated in the figure.
The change in energy, the perturbation Hamiltonian H',
is given by the work done on the system by the external force.
By definition, this is equal to the force times the distance traveled.
Thus, A = R_x.
Since the response function depends on A-dot which is R-dot thus V,
lets take B equals to V to obtain the response in terms of the velocity autocorrelation function.
From the linear response function Eqs. (44) and (45),
the drift velocity under the perturbed Hamiltonian H_0+H'
is represented by the time integral of the velocity autocorrelation function from zero to t
since F=0 for t less than 0.
Even though we assumed a constant force along the x-direction,
this can be generalized to an arbitrary direction to give the general form in expression (46).
In the figure we have illustrated the time evolution of the drift velocity
after the application of external drift force at t=0.
Finally, from Eqs. (43) and (46),
the self diffusion constant of the Brownian particle is obtained by
taking the limit when t goes to infinity.
Linear response theory allows us to replace the average over the perturbed system
with a different average over the unperturbed system.
The final result is shown as Eq. (47).
This is an example of the so-called Green-Kubo formula,
which can define transport coefficients
in terms of equilibrium correlation functions of corresponding variables.
Here we have computed the Diffusion coefficient
in terms of the velocity auto-correlation function of an equilibrium system!