In this plot, I will explain how to draw a graph
using the Jupyter notebook with the matplotlib plotting library,
which is the standard 2D plotting library for Python.
Although we will only introduce
the very basic functions in this plot,
matplotlib can produce various kinds of publication quality figures with minimal effort.
If you are interested in obtaining more information,
you should visit their gallery page
to see examples of the various types of plots can be generated.
First, we should import the libraries needed to make the graphs.
For this, type the following commands
in a new cell and run them.
Note that Python will ignore anything that comes after the # symbol,
it is just a comment that you add to make your code more readable
so you do not have to type them to get the examples to work.
The first line is a 'magic' python command
that controls the environment settings.
Here we are instructing the system to output graphs inside the notebook itself.
If you do not include this command, the graphs will be plotted in separate window.
The second line is used to import the "numpy" library,
which we have already used previously.
The third line is to import the "pyplot" library,
which is a subset of "maplotlib"
and provides a MATLAB-like plotting framework,
use it with a shorter name "plt."
The fourth line is to use a customized style sheet called "ggplot"
which modifies the default plot settings
to produce more beautiful plots.
These libraries will be extensively used in this course
to plot all data and functions.
As the first example
let us try to draw a simple sine function.
Create a new cell and type the following commands, and run them.
You will finally obtain a graph of sin(x)
for x equals from -3 to +3 in a linear scale.
Here the description of each command is not explained in detail
but given as a short comment after #.
If you are unsure about any commands,
please refer to one of the many free online resources
such as the official matplotlib or Python websites.
For the second example we will draw several functions
which are simple powers of X in a log-log scale
First, define the functional form to be plotted
using a "def" block as shown here.
Create a new cell and type the following commands, and run them.
The "def" keyword defines a new function, called "func,"
which takes two parameters x and n.
The function will return x to the power of n.
Then, type the following commands in a new cell and run them
to draw the functions in a log-log scale.
The description of each command is given after #.
The main part is between the second and fourth lines
where the three power functions, x, x^2, and x^3 are plotted versus x.
By plotting them on a log-log scale,
all three functions appear as straight lines
with slopes of one, two and three respectively.
In this example, the labels and legends are also plotted together with
the functions on the same graph.
The third example is to draw a hystogram of a collection of random-data points.
As you can see in the following cell,
the third line generates a sequence of 100,000 random numbers
uniformly distributed between 0 and 1,
and then stores them in an array R.
The fourth line is the main part of this example,
where the normalized histogram of R is calculated using 100 bins
and plotted as a graph using a single command.
Like this, the "hist" function allows us to calculate the histogram of any array data very easily.
Finally, by plotting the histogram, we can confirm that
the distribution of generated random numbers is really uniformly distributed between zero and one.
As you have seen here, Python has very powerful and easy-to-use graphical capabilities.
In particular,
we will repeatedly use the "hist" function in this course.
The fourth example is to draw trajectories of random steps,
which describes a process called a 1-dimensional random walk.
A trajectory means the sequence of temporal positions,
usually as a function of time or number of steps.
In the code example shown here,
the sixth line generates ten trajectories of 10,000 random steps of +1 or -1,
and then stores them in an array named step.
The positions of ten independent random walkers are calculated at each step by accumulating
the individual values of step,
from zero to the number of steps.
Finally, by plotting the position as a function of number of steps,
we can visualize the trajectories of the random walkers.