In this plot we try to simulate the dynamics of a simple mechanical system using the Euler method.
Consider a spring of constant k, with one end attached to the origin,
and the other end to a particle of mass m immersed in a fluid.
Here the friction constant between the particle and the fluid is zeta,
but we assume that the spring is friction free.
Let R(t) be the temporal position of the particle at time t, and V(t) its velocity.
There are two forces acting on the particle;
the friction force exerted by the fluid and the restoring force of the spring.
The friction force is assumed to be proportional to
the velocity of the particle and points in the opposite direction.
The spring force is assumed to be proportional to the distance from the origin and points towards the origin.
Then, the following two differential equations
for the time evolution of the position and the velocity of the particle, must be simultaneously solved.
Eq. (B1) is simply the definition of the velocity,
and Eq. (B2) represents the force balance, which is known as Newton's 2nd law of motion.
We here use the Euler method to numerically solve the ordinary differential Eqs. (B1) and (B2).
For a small time increment Delta t,
the time integrals from t_i to t_i+Delta t can be approximated to first order
as shown in Eqs. (B3) and (B4).
Before running a simulation, let us import the necessary libraries.
In the code examples shown here,
first, we define the dimensionality of our system, and the number of steps we want to take.
Then, define R and V as two-dimensional vectors,
which will contain the instantaneous position and velocity of our particle.
To visualize the trajectory, we also create arrays Rs and Vs,
which will contain the positions and velocities at all times.
Finally, we also define arrays to store the energy and the time values for the whole trajectory.
To create animations using "matplotlib," we will use the "FuncAnimation" procedure of the animation module.
This module requires that we define two additional procedures, "init" and "animate."
"init" is just an initialization procedure that defines all the graphical elements that will later be used.
"animate" is the main procedure. It will be called every time we want to update the graph,
thus, it will be responsible for updating our solution by performing the time integration.
We perform a simulation in the code example shown here.
The System parameters and the initial conditions are defined at the beginning.
Then, necessary procedures for drawing animation are performed.
Finally the "Func.animation" procedure is called at the bottom.
Here, we visualize the time evolution of the particle trajectory.
The black point represents the position of the particle at the given time.
In addition, the entire trajectory of the particle is given by updating the red line at each step.
Notice that the particle traces what appears to be a closed orbit.
Let us look in more detail at what is happening to the particle.
For this, we have plotted the x and y positions as well as the total energy, as a function of time.
As expected, the x and y coordinates show oscillatory motion.
What is probably more surprising are the oscillations in the total energy.
In this case, we have turned off friction, so ideally the energy of our system should be conserved.
The oscillations in the energy are an artifact of the approximate solution scheme we have used.
To reduce these fluctuations, we can use a smaller Delta t,
or even adopt a higher order integrator, for example the Runge-Kutta 4th order method.
However, even though the energy is not strictly conserved,
notice that there is no notable systematic drift.
The energy oscillates around a fixed value.
For physical simulations, this is a crucial aspect of a good integrator.
Ideally, the solutions to this harmonic problem in the absence of friction are closed orbits.
To check if this is the case, we make a parametric plot of the x, y positions of the particle.
Indeed, our orbit appears to be a closed one
even though a more careful examination will show a slightly spiraling trajectory.