In this plot we learn about the Euler method for numerical integration.
It is the most basic explicit method for numerically solving ordinary differential equations.
Although many other methods with higher accuracy have been proposed,
the simplicity of the Euler method makes it ideal when studying the subject for the first time.
We will use it to simulate the motions of Brownian particles
in the remaining part of this course.
Let us consider an ordinary differential equation shown here in Eq. (A1).
We want to know the temporal values of y for any time t,
under the initial condition y=y_0 at t=t_0.
First, let us write down the former solutions of
the differential equation by integrating Eq. (A1) in time, from t_0 to t.
Eq. (A2) gives the exact value of y at any given time t,
starting from the initial condition of y_0 at t=0.
However, an analytical evaluation of the time integrals is only possible for very limited cases.
In most situations, we must solve these differential equations numerically.
The Euler method is the simplest method for performing this numerical integration.
To solve differential equation numerically using computers,
we must first discretize the time axis.
We divide the total time span, from t_0 to t into N equally spaced segments,
each describing a short time increment Delta t.
And define the following discrete valuables.
Now, consider how to perform the integration over a small time increment Delta t,
from t_i to t_i+1.
Using the Taylor expansion,
we expand the integrand around t_i,
in increasing powers of τ, where τ = t' - t_i.
For simplicity, we only explicitly write the zero-th order term, f_i.
The integrals can be performed analytically with each term
one order in Delta t higher than the previous one.
In the limit when the time increment Delta t goes to 0,
we can neglect all terms in Eq. (A7) of second order or higher.
This first order approximation is known as the Euler method, shown here as Eq. (A8).
By repeatedly applying Eq.(A8) N times
we can obtain an approximation of y at a given time t = N Delta t.
This process is schematically shown in Eq. (A9).
This is a typical example of how a computer simulation proceeds.
The Euler method is a first-order method,
which means that the local error is proportional to the square of Delta t,
and the global error is proportional to Delta t.
Although simple not very accurate itself,
the Euler method serves as the basis to construct more accurate methods.
From Eqs. (A1) and (A8),
it is straightforward to solve for f, and to recognize that
the Euler method is a forward difference approximation to the derivative of y,
as defined in Eq. (A10).
Instead of using the forward difference approximation of the Euler method,
we can use a centered difference to design a higher-order integration method.
The central difference approximation given by Eq. (A11) estimates
the derivative of y at step i, in terms of the y values at steps i-1 and i+1.
Substituting Eq. (A11) into Eq. (A1),
we obtain the difference equation referred to as the Leapfrog method, shown in Eq. (A12).
This integration scheme gives a method that is accurate to second order in Delta t.
The simulation procedure corresponding to the Leapfrog method
is schematically represented in Eqs. (A13) and (A14).
In contrast to the Euler method,
the difference equation for the Leapfrog method involves values of y and f at distinct times,
in this case i and i-1 respectively.
Here we have written down the difference equations for a second order Runge-Kutta method.
The first Eq. (A15) represents an intermediate operation
to estimate y of i+1/2 and f of i+1/2 at the midpoint using the Euler method.
The second Eq. (A16) represents the main operation,
where y_i+1 is calculated using a Leapfrog like method
with f evaluated at the midpoint.
This particular method is second order in Delta t, like the Leapfrog method,
but higher order Runge-Kutte methods can be easily derived.
In fact, the most popular Runge-Kutta method is the 4th order method we present now.
The appropriate difference equations for this scheme are given in Eqs. from (A18) to (A21).
The first three equations from (A18) to (A20) represent intermediate operations to estimate
tentative values for y and f using the Euler method.
The fourth equation is the main operation,
where y_i+1 is calculated using the intermediate values of f obtained previously.
This method is fourth order in Delta t.
Let us consider a very simple problem here,
and try to apply the Euler method to numerically solve it.
We want to numerically solve the following differential equation
and determine y for t from 0 to 10, with initial condition y=1 at t=0.
Then, we compare it with the analytical solution y = exponential -t.
As we already learned in the previous lesson,
we should first import the libraries needed to draw the plots.
In the code example shown here,
first, we define the time increment and the time range
as well as the number of integration steps to take.
Next, we create an array for the time values
and the y values for the analytical and numerical solutions.
The numerical solution to y is found by repeated application of Eq. (A8).
Finally, to visualize the error of our method
we plot the ratio of the two solutions.
Although both curves seem identical,
it is clear that for large times, the error increases.
This error can be reduced by decreasing Delta t.